Center for Community Studies; Records ua652.004
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Center for Community Studies Records
1946-1976
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
State University of New York at Albany. Center for Community Studies
ua652.004
14.2 cubic ft.
Created in 1950 in part to study education in school districts. The Center's mission was to identify the research factors that aid in constructing and maintaining strong democratic communities and to promote such factors through education.
Access
Access to student material in Series 2 is restricted. Series 1 and Series 3 are unrestricted. Consult a staff member for details.
Acquisition Information
All items in this collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives. 1988 June
Historical Note
In 1950, the Board of Trustees of the State University of New York accepted a proposal and a $10,000 grant from the Bureau of Intercultural Education for the academic year 1950-1951 and established a Center for Community Studies (CCS). The CCS had its headquarters at the New York State College for Teachers in Albany, New York, although its staff worked with all thirty-three affiliated institutions in the state university system. CCS was set up as a pilot organization with Dr. William E. Vickery, Professor of Intercultural Education, as its director. CCS’s mission was to identify through research factors that aid in constructing and maintaining strong democratic communities and to promote the factors through education. On the basis of modern research in the field of community studies, the staff of CCS chose two main areas in which to experiment. The first of these was rooted in the notion that democratic communities thrive when individuals feel that their input counts and when they believe that they have the right and responsibility to share in community life and to help make important decisions that affect them, their neighbors and their whole community. The second principal for CCS’s research was guided by the idea that communities become stronger when individuals balance their personal needs and desires with those of the community at large. Given the above principles, the staff of CCS set out to find ways to promote participation in community affairs, especially the decision-making process and actions that democratic citizenship imply. It also sought to aid individuals in developing the ability to live and work productively while crossing the lines of race, religion, ethnicity, and membership in socio-economic groups so as to promote the common welfare of the whole community.
One of the most interesting fields for carrying out its mission was teacher education, as it was assumed that all schools reach all of the children of all of the people. It was recognized that how good schools were as training grounds for good community living depended a great deal on their teachers. Consequently, CCS’s working hypothesis was that the field of community studies was an effective means of training such teachers. As an organization, it emphasized its role of alerting teachers to their responsibilities in order to promote better human understanding and constructive thinking in inter-group relations. Teachers were to help their students acquire the ideals, skills and patterns of living necessary for living and working together in a complex modern society. Thus, teachers were expected to become active participants in community affairs to show in their daily lives the respect for other people that characterizes the free, humane and enlightened citizen, and to make their classrooms laboratories where students would learn good citizenship by living it each day. Moreover, the staff of CCS believed strongly that experiences in community studies could not come from books alone. It was thought that undergraduates and teachers in service needed real first-hand experiences in community living under competent guidance and direction. It was also thought that without such guidance and direction, community experience could well discourage further community participation rather than stimulate increased activity in community affairs. In order to fulfill these purposes, the staff of CCS developed several projects in community study and human relations. Their work was carried out according to the interests, needs, and facilities of the participating colleges and communities. The programs of the Center for Community Studies included working with school people, members and affiliates of clubs and other organizations, government workers and officials, lay community leaders, and other community workers in solving problems that required the activation and mobilization of social forces, community interest, and citizen participation. The staff of CCS worked to develop a broader awareness and understanding in communities of individual and community needs. These aims were attained through: classes, workshops and seminars in community organizations during which participants would relate theory to specific problems in their communities; guidance counseling and leadership of specific efforts in a single community or neighborhood to define problems and propose solutions, and act upon them, including work of general and special nature relating to the effective functioning of groups, committees, clubs, associations, etc.; internships in community study and development during which students and others were placed as aids, interns, or in some other position in citizens’ councils or councils of community service so as to work, cooperate and observe; and research to inquire into the processes by which individuals cooperate to solve community problems and broaden their perceptions of community needs.
A key concept of CCS’s approach was the principle of action research developed by Kurt Lewin and his associates as they endeavored to find ways to work effectively toward rational social management and social engineering. Operating on the principles of action research, the Center for Community Studies consisted of three divisions. First, the State University Conference on Community Studies was made up of representatives of each of the eleven state teachers colleges of the State University of New York. This conference helped to formulate CCS policy, stimulated action-research programs on local college campuses, and distributed information about CCS and its activities to other members of their respective faculties. The second division was a five-person executive committee drawn from this Conference whose duties were to screen projects submitted to CCS for support through grants in-aid and to allocate funds to local programs. The Executive Committee also defined issues and problems to present to the Conference for policy decisions. The third was the staff of CCS whose function was to coordinate the program, provide consultant services, administer the research fund, and help the local college communities interpret the program to their colleges. The staff also engaged in research at the colleges and helped the local communities prepare their reports for publication and distribution.
According to the undergraduate and graduate bulletins for the State University of New York at Albany, the Center for Community Studies ceased to exist as a separate entity from the School of Education between the fall of 1964 and the spring of 1966. Its programs and research seem to have been absorbed and restructured as an integral part of the School of Education.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the organization, evolution, scope, thinking, activities and programs of the Center for Community Studies over a period of about 25 years. The earliest items contained in this collection date from 1825 and were part of the Census Classification Project for Albany, New York, but continuous records for the CCS itself start at its inception in 1950 and continue to the apparent date of its disbanding. There are also some records, mostly memos and letters, that postdate the apparent discontinuation of CCS that run up to 1976. Major collectors of records appear to be professors William E. Vickery and Donald Van Cleve.
Topics which are extensively documented in this collection include action research projects, extensive course materials, the Three Wishes Project, the development of educational television, the New York State Citizens’ Council, the Poliomyelitis Project of 1956, in-school testing materials, student and faculty questionnaires, materials on different areas in which CCS was of service to the wider community, student papers, the Study of Opinions on Medicine and Child Health of 1956, the University-Community Cooperation Project and materials on workshops given by CCS. Also contained in this collection are photocopies of street maps of Albany, New York from the 1800s and early 1900s.
Several collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives provide further information on education and policy issues that were of concern to the faculty, staff and students of the Center for Community Studies. For complete listings of related collections, consult the subject guides for University at Albany, SUNY Administrative Records and Education. Of particular note are the records of the Capital Area School Development Association (APAP065) and the School of Education (UA650).
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is unprocessed and is likely disorganized. Individual items may be difficult to find.
Neighborhood and Community Associations; Medicine and Health Care; Ethnic Groups; Teacher education; UAlbany Centers & Institutes; State University of New York at Albany
- Administrative Files, 1950-1976; 1; 1 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of materials relating directly to the operations of the Center for Community Studies and to some of its faculty and staff. The series includes: the records of the activities and programs committees; minutes of the American Red Cross, Albany, New York chapter; Board of Directors of the Council of Community Services; the Inter-group Relations Committee; the Siesta Symposium of 1966; the Subcommittee of the New York State Citizens' Council Field Committee; the Superintendents' Advisory Committee; records pertaining to faculty and staff meetings; alumni; personnel; and recruitment strategies. Other items found in this series include budget materials, Executive Committee meetings, expense accounts, grants, memoranda, and records concerning the Temporary Committee on Graduate Admissions.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Addresses, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Admissions, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Advisory Committee, 1952-1962 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Advisory Committee on Social Work Administration, 1963-1964 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Advisory Group of School Superintendents, 1963 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Albany Community Chest, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Alphabetical List of Agencies, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Alumni, 1966 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - American Red Cross, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Annual Report, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Annual Report of the Director, 1951 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Annual Report of the Director, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Annual Report of the Director, 1952 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Annual Research Convocation, 1962 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Awards, 1975 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
  - Bibliography, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 16)
  - Board of Directors, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 17)
  - Budget, 1952-1954 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 18)
  - Campus Academic Plan, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 19)
  - Classification System, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 20)
  - Committee for May Dinner, 1951-1952 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 21)
  - Committee on Administration, 1951 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 22)
  - Committee on Advanced Programs, 1976 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 23)
  - Committee on Advanced Studies in Education, 1966 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 24)
  - Committee on Doctoral Programs in Education, 1960-1964 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 25)
  - Committee on Intergroup Relations 1952-54, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 26)
  - Committee Reports, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 27)
  - Cooperation with Social Science Division, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 28)
  - Department of Education, 1956 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 29)
  - Department of Foundations of Education, 1966-1967 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 30)
  - Directory, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 31)
  - Dissertation Seminar Committee, 1963-1964 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 32)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1952-1953 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 33)
  - Expense Accounts, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 34)
  - Faculties Association, 1962 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 35)
  - Faculty Meetings, 1964-1966 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 36)
  - Faculty Meetings, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 37)
  - Faculty, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 38)
  - Graduate Academic Council, 1964-1967 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 39)
  - Graduate Sequence Committee, 1962 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 40)
  - Grants, 1963 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 41)
  - Guidelines for Certification, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 42)
  - History and Mission, 1953 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 43)
  - Intergroup Relations Committee, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 44)
  - Memoranda, 1964-1973 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 45)
  - New York State Association of Councils and Chests, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 46)
  - New York State Citizens Council Field Committee, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 47)
  - Nominating Committee, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 48)
  - Personnel, 1966-1967 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 49)
  - Personnel, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 50)
  - Policy and Procedures on Continuing Appointments, 1972 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 51)
  - Problems Census Committee, 1950-1951 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 52)
  - Recruitment, 1964-1965 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 53)
  - Siesta Symptoms, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 54)
  - Staff Meetings, 1951-1952 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 55)
  - State University Committee on Community Studies, 1956 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 56)
  - Subcommittee on Organization and Homemaker Study Committee, 1956 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 57)
  - Superintendents Advisory Committee and the Faculty in Educational Administration, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 58)
  - Temporary Committee on Graduate Admissions, 1973 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 59)
  - Vita, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 60)
  - Advisory Committee Meetings, 1952 (Box 14 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Annual Report of the Center for Community Studies, 1951-1952 (Box 14 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Staff Meetings, 1952 (Box 14 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
- Activities and Programs, 1825-1976; 2; 12 cubic ft.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Student material is restricted, must consult archivist to view material.
  This series contains materials relating directly to the activities and programs of the Center for Community Studies. Topics of interest include action research projects, extensive course materials, the Three Wishes Project, the development of educational television, the New York State Citizens' Council, the Poliomyelitis Project of 1956, in-school testing materials, student and faculty questionnaires and study notes, materials on different areas in which CCS was of service to the wider community, student papers and projects, the Study of Opinions on Medicine and Child Health of 1956, the University-Community Cooperation Project, and materials on workshops given by CCS. This series is restricted due to the inclusion of student material. Consult a member of the Department of Special Collections and Archives' staff for further details.
  - Abrams, Charles, Chapter 2: "Implications of the Studies", Undated (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 61)
  - Academic Freedom, 1952-1954 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 62)
  - Action for Cultural Enrichment Project, Undated (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 63)
  - Action Research, Brockport State Teachers College, 1951 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 64)
  - Action Research, Buffalo State Teachers College, 1951-1952 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 65)
  - Action Research, Fredonia State Teachers College, 1951-1953 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 66)
  - Action Research, Geneseo State Teachers College, 1952-1953 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 67)
  - Action Research, Oneonta State Teachers College, 1951 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 68)
  - Action Research, State Teachers College Oswego, 1951 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 69)
  - The ADA Craig Walker Award, Undated (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 70)
  - Student, SOC 110: Intergroup Relations, 1951 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 71)
  - Albany AAUP, 1963-1964 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 72)
  - Albany Adult Education Department, 1953 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 73)
  - Albany Council of Community Services, Undated (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 74)
  - Albany Community Chest Project, 1948-1951 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 75)
  - Albany Community Project, Undated (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 76)
  - Albany County Department of Health, Annual Report, 1953 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 77)
  - Albany Neighborhood Study, 1954 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 78)
  - Student, SOC 110: Intergroup Relations, 1952 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 1)
  - Student, Student Report, 1951 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 2)
  - American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, 1952 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 3)
  - American Cyanamid Company, 1951 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 4)
  - Analysis of Three Wishes Project, 1952 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 5)
  - Annual Curriculum Conference for School Administrations, Undated (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 6)
  - The Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development, 1953 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 7)
  - Student, 1951 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 8)
  - Bard, B, "Guide for Future Teachers," New York Post, 1961 February 27 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 9)
  - Student, "An Analysis of the Heavenly City of the Eighteenth Century Philosphers", Undated (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 10)
  - Student, "Friedrich Froebel", 1976 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 11)
  - Student, "The Theory of Michael De Montaigne, 1976 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 12)
  - Student, SOC 408 Final Exam, 1961 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 13)
  - Berger, M.I., "School and Society", 1957 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 14)
  - Student, "School Taxes and Public Relations", 1952 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 15)
  - Student, Education 317 Report, 1951 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 16)
  - Bibliographies, 1953-1954 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 17)
  - Bibliography for Local History, 1952-1953 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 18)
  - Book Fair, Undated (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 19)
  - Books on Reserve, 1949 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 20)
  - Student,, "Television as a Medium of Education and Its Role in Educational Public Relations", 1952 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 21)
  - The Brockport Delinquency Conference, 1955 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 22)
  - Brown School, Student Subjects, Undated (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 23)
  - Brubacher, John S. "A Proposal for Judging What Is and What Is Not Progressive Education", 1956 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 24)
  - Student, Education 301A: Philosophy of Education, 1957 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 25)
  - Bureau for Intercultural Education, 1950-1952 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 26)
  - Student, Student Project, 1976 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 27)
  - Cali, A.J., Some Observations Concerning the School Administration and Public Problems in the Sixties, 1960 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 28)
  - Student, Project and Exam, 1961 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 29)
  - Camp Rising Sun, Louis A. Jonas Foundation, 1950-1952 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 30)
  - Campo, Anthony, SOC 408 Final Exam, 1961 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 31)
  - Capital Area School Boards Institute, Undated (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 32)
  - Capital Area School Development Association, 1955-1956 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 33)
  - Capital Area School Development Association, Human Relations through English Group, 1952 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 34)
  - Capital Area School Development Association, Workshop, 1951 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 35)
  - The Case for Modern Man, 1963-1965 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 36)
  - Student, Educational Philosophy 601, 1976 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 37)
  - Center for Intergroup Education, the University of Chicago, 1949 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 38)
  - Central New York School Study Council, 1964 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 39)
  - Childs, John L. "John Dewey and Education", Undated (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 40)
  - The Citizens Advisory Committee on Housing, Research Report No. 1, 1953 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 41)
  - Citizens Committee for Albany Public Schools, 1953 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 42)
  - Student, SOC 110: Intergroup Relations, 1951 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 43)
  - Clark, Norman, Director of Clinton Square Neighborhood House, 1951 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 44)
  - Student, Education 317, 1951 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 45)
  - Code Sheet Project X Stencil, Undated (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 46)
  - Student, "An Exploratory Study of the Status of Hierarchy of Selected High School Occupations", 1963 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 47)
  - Student, SOC 110: Intergroup Relations, 1951 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 48)
  - The College Study in Intergroup Relations by Lloyd Allen Cook, 1946 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 49)
  - Collegiate Association for Development of Educational Administration in New York State (CADEA), 1962-1964 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 50)
  - Colloquia, 1976 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 51)
  - Student, Education 317, 1951 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 52)